<refentry xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
          xmlns:cx="http://xmlcalabash.com/ns/extensions"
          xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
          xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
          xmlns:p="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc"
          xml:id="p.string-replace">
<refnamediv>
<refname><step>p:string-replace</step></refname>
<refpurpose>Replaces matched nodes with the result of evaluating an XPath expression</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<refsynopsisdiv>
<p:declare-step type="p:string-replace">
   <p:input port="source"/>
   <p:output port="result"/>
   <p:option name="match" required="true" cx:type="XSLTMatchPattern"/>
   <p:option name="replace" required="true" cx:type="XPathExpression"/>
</p:declare-step>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsection>
<title>Description</title>

<para>The <step>p:string-replace</step> step replaces matched nodes
with the result of evaluating an XPath expression. In other words, it
allows you to identify a node (or nodes) in the document, perform a
computation on that node, and then update the document to contain the
result of that computation instead of the original node.</para>

<para>More technically, the <step>p:string-replace</step> step
replaces nodes in the document provided on the <port>source</port>
port that match the pattern specified in the <option>match</option>
option with the string result of evaluating the XPath expression
specified in the <option>replace</option> option.</para>

<para>For each node in the document provided on the
<port>source</port> port:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>If the match pattern specified in the <option>match</option> option
matches the node, then the XPath expression provided in the
<option>replace</option> option is evaluated with the matched node
as the context.</para>
<para>If the node is an attribute node then the string value of the
expression replaces the attribute <emphasis>value</emphasis>, if the
node is any other kind of node, then the string value of the
expression replaces the entire node (not just the content of the
node).</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>If the match pattern does not match the node, then the string replace
operation is performed on each of the node's attributes (if it is an element)
and its children. The resulting, transformed node is copied to the output.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>One of the least convenient parts of the
<step>p:string-replace</step> step is the <option>replace</option>
option. What you must always bear in mind is that the value of the
<option>replace</option> option is treated as an XPath expression
<emphasis>by the step</emphasis>.</para>

<para>Often, this is what you want. Unfortunately, in one of the most
common cases, where you'd like to replace an attribute value with some
computed value, the obvious approach does not do what you'd
expect.</para>

<para>Consider this pipeline:</para>

<programlisting
><xi:include href="examples/string-replace-ex1.xpl" parse="text"
/></programlisting>

<para>On the surface, this pipeline appears to replace the value of
the <att>class</att> attribute with the value passed to the pipeline
in the <option>new-class</option> option. The string replace step is
effectively the same as this one:
</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[  <p:string-replace match="p/@class" replace="new-value">
    <p:input port="source">
      <p:inline><p class="old-value">Some text.</p></p:inline>
    </p:input>
  </p:string-replace>]]></programlisting>

<para>Here we can see that the value of the <option>replace</option> option
is a bare name. Recall that <step>p:string-replace</step> treats the value
of <option>replace</option> <emphasis>as an XPath expression</emphasis>.
A bare name in XPath selects child elements with that name. So, as written,
what this string replace step does is replace the value of the <att>class</att>
attribute with the string value of its <tag>new-value</tag> element children.</para>

<para>Of course, attributes don't have element children, so the result of
evaluating that XPath expression is always the empty string and that's the
value that will be used for the <att>class</att> attribute.</para>

<para>The step that we need to evaluate effectively is this one:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[  <p:string-replace match="p/@class" replace="'new-value'">
    <p:input port="source">
      <p:inline><p class="old-value">Some text.</p></p:inline>
    </p:input>
  </p:string-replace>]]></programlisting>

<para>That can be achieved in the following way:</para>

<programlisting
><xi:include href="examples/string-replace-ex2.xpl" parse="text"
/></programlisting>

<para>Which is undeniably pretty ugly.</para>

</refsection>

<refsection>
<title>Examples</title>

<xi:include href="build/string-replace.xml" xpointer="xpath(/*/*)"/>

</refsection>

</refentry>
