<refentry xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
          xmlns:cx="http://xmlcalabash.com/ns/extensions"
          xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
          xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
          xmlns:p="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc"
          xml:id="p.xslt">
<refnamediv>
<refname><step>p:xslt</step></refname>
<refpurpose>Performs XSLT processing</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<refsynopsisdiv>
<p:declare-step type="p:xslt">
  <p:input port="source" sequence="true" primary="true"/>
  <p:input port="stylesheet"/>
  <p:input port="parameters" kind="parameter"/>
  <p:output port="result" primary="true"/>
  <p:output port="secondary" sequence="true"/>
  <p:option name="initial-mode" cx:type="xsd:QName"/>
  <p:option name="template-name" cx:type="xsd:QName"/>
  <p:option name="output-base-uri" cx:type="xsd:anyURI"/>
  <p:option name="version" cx:type="xsd:string"/>
</p:declare-step>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsection>
<title>Description</title>

<para>The <tag>p:xslt</tag> step applies an
<biblioref linkend="xslt10"/> or
<biblioref linkend="xslt20"/> stylesheet to a document.</para>

<para>If the step specifies a <option>version</option>, then that
version of XSLT is used to process the transformation. If the step
does not specify a version, the implementation may use any version it
has available and may use any means to determine what version to use,
including, but not limited to, examining the version of the
stylesheet.</para>

<para>The XSLT stylesheet provided on the <port>stylesheet</port> port
is applied to the document on the <port>source</port> port. Any
parameters passed on the <port>parameters</port> port are used to
define top-level stylesheet parameters. The primary result document of
the transformation appears on the <port>result</port> port. All other
result documents appear on the <port>secondary</port> port. If XSLT
1.0 is used, an empty sequence of documents always
appears on the <port>secondary</port> port.</para>

<para>If a sequence of documents is provided on the
<port>source</port> port, the first document is used as the
primary input document. The whole sequence is also the default
collection.
If no documents are provided on the <port>source</port> port,
the primary input document is undefined and the default collection
is empty.
</para>

<para>A dynamic error occurs if the XSLT processor signals a fatal
error. This includes the case where the transformation terminates due
to a <tag>xsl:message</tag> instruction with a <tag
class="attribute">terminate</tag> attribute value of
“<literal>yes</literal>”. How XSLT message termination errors
are reported to the XProc processor is
<glossterm>implementation-dependent</glossterm>.</para>

<para>The invocation of the transformation is controlled by the
<option>initial-mode</option> and <option>template-name</option>
options that set the initial mode and/or named template in the XSLT
transformation where processing begins.
</para>

<para>The <option>output-base-uri</option> option sets the context's
output base URI per the XSLT 2.0 specification, otherwise the base URI
of the <port>result</port> document is the base URI of the first
document in the <code>source</code> port's sequence. If the value of
the <option>output-base-uri</option> option is not absolute, it will
be resolved using the base URI of its <tag>p:option</tag>
element. An XSLT 1.0 step should use the value of the
<option>output-base-uri</option> as the base URI of its output, if the
option is specified.</para>

<para>If XSLT 2.0 is used, the outputs of this step may include PSVI
annotations.</para>

</refsection>

<refsection>
<title>Errors</title>
<informaltable>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colwidth="1in"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Error</entry>
<entry>Description</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry><error code="C0038"/></entry>
<entry>Occurs
if the specified version of XSLT
is not available.
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><error code="C0039"/></entry>
<entry>Occurs
if a sequence of documents (including
an empty sequence) is provided
to an XSLT 1.0 step.
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><error code="C0056"/></entry>
<entry>Occurs
if the specified initial mode
or named template cannot be applied to the specified stylesheet.
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</refsection>

<refsection>
<title>Examples</title>

<para>FIXME: tbd.</para>

</refsection>

</refentry>
