<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:cx="http://xmlcalabash.com/ns/extensions"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:p="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc"
         version="5.0-xproc" xml:id="steps">
<info>
<title>Steps and Connections</title>
</info>

<para>Steps perform units of work. How those steps are connected together
determines the overall result of a pipeline. As
<link linkend="connection-direction">we said</link> in
<xref linkend="terminology"/>, connections in XProc are always written
from the perspective of the step with the input port.</para>

<para>Inputs can be connected, or “bound”, in four different ways. An
input can be connected to:</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>A <link linkend="p.document">document</link> identified by a
URI. “Read from <uri>http://example.com/document.xml</uri>.”</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>An output <link linkend="p.port">port</link> on another step
in the pipeline.
“Read the output of the <port>result</port> port on that
<tag>p:xslt</tag> step.”</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>A <link linkend="p.inline">literal document</link> specified
inline in the pipeline. “Take this XML from the pipeline,
create a document out of it, and use it as the input.”</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>An <link linkend="p.empty">explicitly empty</link> sequence.
“Read nothing.”</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>If an input port accepts a sequence of documents, then more than
one input binding can be specified and the various kinds of connections
can be mixed arbitrarily.</para>

<para>If an input port has no explicit connections, then it will
automatically be connected to the
<link linkend="default-readable">default readable port</link>, if
there is one. It's an error to leave an input port unconnected, so if there
is neither an explicit connection nor a default readable port, the pipeline
is not valid.</para>

<section xml:id="input.connections">
<title>Input Connections</title>

<para>The most common kind of input is a <tag>p:input</tag>, an input
to an atomic step, but several other kinds of inputs exist. Each is
conceptually an input, but they were given their own names because
they exhibit some differences from a standard input:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para><tag>p:iteration-source</tag> on <tag>p:for-each</tag>. The
<tag>p:for-each</tag> has only a single input and it doesn't have a name.
It functions as the input to the <tag>p:for-each</tag> step.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><tag>p:viewport-source</tag> on <tag>p:viewport</tag>. Like
<tag>p:for-each</tag>, the
<tag>p:viewport</tag> has only a single input and it doesn't have a name.
It functions as the input to the <tag>p:viewport</tag> step.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><tag>p:xpath-context</tag> on <tag>p:choose</tag> and <tag>p:when</tag>.
The XPath context in a <tag>p:choose</tag> is also an input. It has no name
and special defaulting rules apply. It establishes the document that
is the context node for evaluating the test expressions.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><tag>p:variable</tag> in a compound step. The value of a variable is
determined by evaluating an XPath expression; the binding for that
<tag>p:variable</tag> establishes the document that is the context node
for the expression.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><tag>p:with-option</tag> and <tag>p:with-param</tag> on steps.
Like variables, the values of options and parameters are
determined by evaluating an XPath expression; the bindings for them
establish the document that is the context node
for their expressions.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>You can think of each of these items as being “bindable”, capable of having
a document (or documents) bound to them. As we'll see in
<xref linkend="dependencies"/>, all of these bindings may be relevant in
determining the order in which steps are evaluated.</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="input.select">
<title>Selecting parts of a document</title>

<para>Ordinary <tag>p:input</tag> connections and <tag>p:iteration-source</tag>
inputs can include a <tag class="attribute">select</tag> expression. If a select
expression is specified, then all of the elements in each input document that
match the specified expression are used as the input. In this case, each matching
node is converted into a document in its own right <emphasis>and</emphasis> the
parts of the document that did not match the select expression are effectively
ignored.</para>

<para>It's important to remember that the input to a step is a
document or a sequence of documents. When a select expression is used,
all the elements selected are effectively extracted from their
original documents and turned into documents in their own right. (This
may have an impact on ID/IDREF links, if there are any.)</para>

<para>Consider the following input statement:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[<p:input port="source">
  <p:document href="homepage.xhtm"/>
</p:input>]]></programlisting>

<para>What this input does is provide, for the step on which it occurs,
a sequence of documents on the “<port>source</port>” input port. That sequence
of documents consists of the single XHTML document identified by the URI
“<uri>homepage.xhtm</uri>”. (In this and many other cases, the
sequence will be exactly one document, but that is not necessarily the
case for a <tag>p:input</tag>.)</para>

<para>In contrast, consider this input statement:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[<p:input xmlns:h="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         port="source" select="/h:html/h:body/h:div">
  <p:document href="homepage.xhtm"/>
</p:input>]]></programlisting>

<para>This input provides a sequence of documents on the
“<port>source</port>” input port as well. In this case, that sequence consists
of one document for every top level <tag>h:div</tag> that occurs in
the document identified by the URI “<uri>homepage.xhtm</uri>”.</para>

<para>(If the select expression had been instead “<code>//h:div</code>”, then
there would have been one document for every <tag>h:div</tag> in the
document. In the case of nested divisions, this would have resulted in (copies
of) the
same nodes appearing in more than one document.)</para>

<para>When you use a select expression, you may change the number of documents
that appear on the port. You can reduce a sequence of documents to a single
document, or produce a sequence of documents from a single document. The step
on which the input occurs will only know about the result after applying the
select expression. This means, for example, that you could send 1,000 documents
to an input that didn't accept a sequence if you also provided a select expression
that would select only a single element from all those documents.</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="dependencies">
<title>Dependencies and the Order of Execution</title>

<para>Most of the pipelines you write will probably be pretty
straightforward. Even as your experience with XProc grows and you
tackle more and more complex problems with it, you're not likely to
write pipelines that are intentionally obfuscated: if step “A”
produces output that step “B” consumes, you'll probably put the “A”
step before the “B” step in your pipeline document.</para>

<para>You'll probably take advantage of the
<link linkend="default-readable">default readable port</link> to simplify
your pipelines. This will naturally lead to a “top to bottom” flow
in your pipelines.</para>

<para>Unfortunately, a pipeline processor can't rely on the organization
that you'll probably use. The processor has to analyze your pipeline and
determine a specific order in which to run the steps.</para>

<para>The processor uses two rules to determine the order in which to
run steps:</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Any step “Y” that consumes the output of another step “X” (i.e., has an
input binding to some output port of “X”) <emphasis>must</emphasis> run
<emphasis>after</emphasis> step “X”.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>It is an error if any step consumes its own output, either directly
or indirectly.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>The second rule means that you can't form a loop of dependencies. Such a
pipeline isn't valid and can't be run. In the terms of our “flowing water”
analogy, this is the equivalent of connecting the output of some box to the
input of some box that's “above” it. Water just doesn't flow that way.</para>

<para>If there are no loops in a pipeline, then there is at least
one way to arrange all the steps pipeline such that every step
is run after every step on which it depends.</para>

<para>Technically, this is a
<emphasis xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Partially_ordered_set">partial
order</emphasis>. Consider the pipeline in <xref linkend="fig.depends"/>.</para>

<figure xml:id="fig.depends">
<title>A dependency graph</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="images/depends.png"/>
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>If we enforce the constraint that every step must run
<emphasis>after</emphasis> every step that it depends on, one possible
way to run this pipeline is to run the steps in this order: A, B, C,
D, E, F. But that constraint is equally satisfied by this order: A, D, B,
C, E, F. Or A, B, D, E, C, F.</para>

<para>The situation is even more obvious in <xref linkend="fig.parallel"/>.
</para>

<figure xml:id="fig.parallel">
<title>Indendent pipelines</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="images/parallel.png"/>
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>Here we have a pipeline with four steps, but the A/B and C/D pipelines
are entirely independent. Any order that preserves the constraint that B runs
after A and D runs after C is acceptable.</para>

<para>The point I'm trying to make is that you can't rely on a processor
running steps in any order that isn't determined by the connections between
the steps.</para>

<tip role="extension">
<para>XML Calabash has an extension attribute that allows you to assert
additional dependencies. You can use the attribute
<tag class="attribute">cx:depends-on</tag> on any step. The value of the
attribute is the name of a step that you want to make sure the processor
runs before it runs the step on which you've placed the extension
attribute.</para>
</tip>
</section>

</chapter>
